Finding Aid for Panhellenic Association (University of Michigan) records, 1945-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Panhellenic Association (University of Michigan) records 1945-1991
University of Michigan. Panhellenic Association.
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
7.5 linear feet
921081 Bimu F45 2 Outsize
The records of the University of Michigan Panhellenic Association contain meeting minutes, annual officers' reports, newspaper clippings, presidents reports, scrapbooks, photographs, printed materials, posters and broadsides. The records document the administration and history of the Panhel at the University of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Panhellenic Association in August 1991. A second accession was transferred in March 1992. (Donor # 7967 ).
The record group is open for research.
The Panhellenic Association (Panhel) is the coordinating, student organization for sororities at the University of Michigan. Panhel grew out of a need for a body to oversee and regulate Rush, the recruitment of new members by sororities, in the early 1900s, and its concerns have gradually expanded over the years to include promotion of sorority cooperation and maintenance of high sorority standards. "As a student accepts membership in a sorority," notes one writer, "she also becomes a member of the total Panhellenic effort." (Box 8, f: Brochures, " Sorority Houses: A Historical Perspective," 1983)
The first sorority at the University of Michigan was founded in 1879. By 1904, there were nine sororities established on campus, and "the need to establish basic group regulations for rushing was an urgent problem." (The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, Vol. 4, p. 1805) One of these original regulations stipulated that meetings of the Inter-Sorority Association, which later became Panhel, were to be held during the rushing season. From this early organization, Panhel grew into an organization with year-round responsibilities.
The internal structure of Panhel has varied over the years, but the two decision-making bodies have been the Executive Council and the Panhellenic Council. The members of the Executive Council are the president, vice president, secretary, treasurer, and committee chairmen. According to the 1981 Constitution, the responsibilities of this council are to administer Rush and to serve as the judicial body of Panhel in instances of constitution violation. (Box 1, f: History and Constitution, "Constitution of the University of Michigan Women's Panhellenic Association of the National Panhellenic Conference (Amended 1981)")
The Panhellenic Council is the administrative body of Panhel and is composed of the Executive Council members and one representative from each sorority. It is the responsibility of this council, according to the 1981 Constitution, "to administer all business related to the overall welfare of The University of Michigan Women's Panhellenic Association and to compile rules governing the Panhellenic Association, including rushing and pledging, which do not violate the sovereignty, rights, and privileges of member fraternities." The Panhellenic Council was previously named the Presidents' Council and consisted of the Executive Council and the presidents of each sorority. At some point after the name was changed to Panhellenic Council, the Gavel Club was organized. The Gavel Club is an advisory group consisting of all sorority presidents who meet to discuss common problems and strengthen relations between houses. Overseeing and supervising all of Panhellenic activities is the Panhellenic Advisor, a university staff member. The Persephones Consilium, a group of sorority alumnae and active members, is responsible for hiring and supervising the Panhellenic Advisor.
The Executive Council and the Panhellenic Council meet weekly to discuss events and activities of interest to all sororities, including Rush, Greek Week, social activities, academic requirements, and Ann Arbor community relations. Rush is a series of social events designed to bring sorority members and prospective members together and formally occurs twice a year at the beginning of the fall and winter semesters. The Panhellenic Council is responsible for devising and distributing Rush rules for each Rush period. Greek Week is "a tradition that began in 1940 as a two day conference for new fraternity initiates as a way to educate them about fraternity life... In 1979, after being dormant for twenty years, Greek Week re-emerged. Greeks were reunited in a week of activities devoted to raising money for charity". (Box 8, f: Brochures, "Rush," 1986) Greek Week occurs in the Spring of each academic year.
The records of the Panhellenic Association (Panhel) measure 7.5 linear feet and include one outsize scrapbook and an outsize folder. The records date from 1945 to 1991 and consist of meeting minutes, annual officers' reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, printed materials, and posters. Despite the range of years covered by the collection as a whole, no one time period is completely documented. For additional information on the history of Panhel, the researcher should consult the folders under the heading "Sororities" in the University of Michigan Library Clipping File and the folder "Panhellenic" in the Vertical File at the Bentley Historical Library.
The records of Panhel are divided into six series: Topical Files, President's Reports, Scrapbooks, Photographs, Printed Materials, and Posters and Broadsides.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Panhellenic Association.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
College publications.; Scrapbooks.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1 linear foot) is arranged alphabetically and consists primarily of materials relating to the activities of Panhel within the university's Greek system. The "Meeting Minutes" folders comprise the bulk of this series and contain the most detailed information regarding issues and concerns facing Panhel. For general information, the "History and Constitution" folder contains descriptive articles and other background material on Panhel, including different versions of the constitution. The "Award Applications" folders offer information regarding community service and philanthropic activities of both Panhel and individual sororities. Also of interest are the "Surveys, Questionnaires, and Evaluations" folders which summarize prevailing campus attitudes toward sororities. The "Membership Selection" folder, received in the 1992 accession, focuses on racial discrimination in the Greek system at the University of Michigan.
  - Annual Report 1980/81 (Box 1)
  - Award Applications
    - National
      - College Panhellenic Committee Award 1978 (Box 1)
      - Exhibits 1981 (award unknown) (Box 1)
      - Fraternity Month Award 1981 (Box 1)
      - National Panhellenic Conference Award
        - 1978 (Box 1)
        - 1981 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan (Box 1)
      - Panhellenic Philanthropy Awards 1980/81-1981/82 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Budget
    - 1973/74-1982/83, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - Fraternity/Sorority Cooperative Housing Code Study Group 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Greek Week
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Hazing 1981 (Box 1)
  - History and Constitution 1965-1984 (Box 1)
  - House Raiding 1975, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Conference 1979, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Advisory Board Chairmen 1979 (August) (Box 1)
    - Executive Council
      - February-March 1964/65 (Box 1)
      - September-January 1965/66 (Box 1)
      - February 1972/73 (Box 1)
    - Gavel Club 1978-1979, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Panhellenic Council
      - October, February 1970/71 (Box 1)
      - February 1971/72 (Box 1)
      - February 1972/73 (Box 1)
      - December-April 1975/7 (Box 1)
      - September-November 1976/77 (Box 1)
      - 1977/78-1987/88, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - January-April 1988/89 (Box 1)
      - September-November 1989/90 (Box 1)
    - Persephones Consilium 1979/80-1983/84 (Box 1)
    - Presidents' Council
      - 1964/65 (Box 1)
      - September-February 1965/66 (Box 1)
  - Office Space Needs 1977 (Box 1)
  - Panhellenic Advisor 1978 (Box 1)
  - Parking Ordinance, 1980-81 (Box 1)
  - Plant Sales, 1980-83 (Box 1)
  - Recolonization Study (re: re-establishment of closed sororities) 1975 and 1979 (Box 1)
  - Junior Panhellenic Association 1963 and undated (Box 7)
  - Membership Selection 1965-1968 (Box 7)
    (re. racial discrimination in the Greek system at the University of Michigan)
- President's Reports
  The President's Reports series (4 linear feet) is comprised of both unbound materials (dating primarily from 1956/57 to 1965/66) and nine bound volumes (covering the years 1959/60 to 1963/64). The title of this series is slightly misleading; an annual report is actually prepared by each executive officer of Panhel summarizing their experiences and achievements. The unbound reports consist only of these annual reports. The bound materials are extensive and include a wide variety of materials from each given year, such as meeting minutes, constitution and bylaws, newsclippings, and invitations to social events. Because the bound reports are so comprehensive, they are one of the best sources of information on Panhellenic activities and policies.
  - Unbound (Box 2)
    - 1956/57 (Box 2)
    - 1958/59-1960/61, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1962/63 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1964/65-1965/66, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1977/78 (Treasurer's Report only) (Box 2)
  - Bound (Box 3)
    - 1959/60-1960/61, 3 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1961/62-1962/63, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1962/63-1963/64, 3 volumes (Box 5)
    - Junior Panhellenic Association 1963 and undated (Box 7)
  - Membership Selection 1965-1968 (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series (1 linear foot) consists of three scrapbooks for the years 1945-1949, 1966-1968, and 1973-1978. The scrapbooks contain interesting clippings regarding all aspects of sorority life and Panhellenic activities, such as Greek Week, Rush and other social events, but also cover such issues as racial discrimination in sororities. The magazine and newspaper clippings come from a variety of publications, but most frequently from The Michigan Daily, the university's student newspaper.
  - 1945-1949 (Volume 1)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 6)
  - 1973-1978 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (.5 linear feet) covers the years from 1933 to 1990, but the majority of the photographs date from the late 1970s and early 1980s. The images mostly depict Greek-related activities, but also include exterior photographs of the sorority houses and interior shots of sorority life.
  - Bed Race undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Derby Days 1977, color positive prints) (Box 7)
  - Greek Week 1986, 1988-1990, color positive prints (Box 7)
  - Group Activities and Stage Performances undated, black and white, and color positive prints, and two color slides (Box 7)
  - Group Shots undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Hill Street Rock Painting undated, black and white, and color positive prints, and one 1988 color slide (Box 7)
  - Leapfrog undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Mass Meeting, Fall 1976, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Mr. Greek Week undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Mudbowl 1981, 1982, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Panhellenic Masquerade Ball October 24, 1986, color positive prints (Box 7)
  - Parade Float undated, color positive prints (Box 7)
  - Plant Sales undated, color positive prints (Box 7)
  - Rush, Fall 1976, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Sorority Houses, mounted undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Sorority Life: interior shots, some with individuals and groups; 1968, 1969, undated, black and white, and color positive prints (Box 7)
  - TKE Fire Engine Ride to Football Game 1967, color positive print (Box 7)
  - Tug of War undated, black and white positive prints, and one color slide (Box 7)
  - Waiter Race undated, black and white positive prints (Box 7)
  - Women's Baseball Team: 6 members, seated on Palmer Field 1933, black and white positive print (Box 7)
- Newsclippings
  The newspaper clippings are from the years 1950-1970 and are mostly from The Michigan Daily. The newspaper clippings focus on racial discrimination in the Greek system at the University of Michigan.
  - 1950-1959, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 7)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1964-1966, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 7)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series (.5 linear feet) contains brochures, bulletins, calendars, and newsletters from the years 1964 to 1991 produced by Panhellenic for its members and includes promotional materials on Rush and Greek Week. For additional information, researchers should consult the printed catalog in the Bentley Historical Library under the headings University of Michigan. Women's League and University of Michigan. Assembly Association.
  - Brochures
    - General
      - Sorority Rush, 1982-1987, 1989 (Box 8)
        (see shelf list for more recent holdings)
      - Sorority Houses: A Historical Perspective, 1983 (Box 8)
  - Bulletins
    - Panhellenic, 1947, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Panhellenic Presents Penny's Postals, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Rush Manual, 1967/1968 (Box 8)
    - Rushing at Michigan, 1952 (Box 8)
    - Sorority houses: a historical perspective, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Sororities at Michigan / Sororities at the University of Michigan, 1942, 1968 1977/1978 1979/1980 and undated (Box 8)
    - Sororities in Perspective, 1964/65 (Box 8)
    - Sorority Rush, 1973, 1984-1989 (Box 8)
    - Sorority Spectrum, 1964-1965 (Box 8)
  - Calendars
    - Greek Week 1980, 1985-1986, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Constitution and Bylaws, 1926/1927 1932/1934 1938, 1962 1962/1963 1964-1965, 1968, 1970, 1973, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Newsletters
      - The Affiliate, February-November 1957 and December 1958 (Box 8)
      - Ann Arbor Alumnae Newsletter, undated (Box 8)
      - Iota, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Panorama, 1960 (October-November) (Box 8)
      - The Reporter, 1961 (October) (Box 8)
      - UM-Pa-Pa, 1974/1975 (Box 8)
      - What the Panhel?, 1980-1984 (Box 8)
    - Programs 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - Regulations
      - University of Michigan Inter-Sorority Association Rushing Rules 1927 and 1928 (Box 8)
      - Panhellenic Rushing Guide 1961-1962 (Box 8)
    - Reports
      - Assembly Panhellenic Spring Rush Study circa 1958 (Box 8)
    - Resolutions
      - Freedom and Responsibility Resolution by National Panhellenic Conference 1961 (Box 8)
- Posters and Broadsides
  There are ten, color Posters and Broadsides which primarily date from 1987 to 1991. The posters were displayed on campus to announce Panhellenic's major campus activities, including Rush, Greek Week, and fund raising events.
  - Posters and Broadsides, undated 1984-1985, 1987-1991 (Folder Bimu/F45)
  - Poster of Panhellenic Fashion Show 1985 (Folder Bimu/F45)